# Michael Lee

Data & Research Professional

Phone: 414-550-3410 Email: mdlee12@amail.com

Washington, DC

# SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

3+ years applying open source libraries to analyze data and build products that drive knowledge acquisition and decision making. Whether working independently or collaboratively I'm able to contribute meaningful work through strong communication skills, critically thinking through challenging data problems, and valuing the impact of diverse audiences when creating products.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# **RESEARCH ASSOCIATE**

American Institutes for Research (July 2015 - Present)

- Co-authored the <u>EdSurvey</u> R package for analysis of survey data using NCES statistical methods, including the development of R functions from scratch (accompanied by acceptance tests), two vignettes, and presentation of the package's practical use for researchers at 2016 and 2017 AERA workshops
- Co-authored the NAEPprimer data package
- Collaborated with designers to replicate a visualization using base R graphics tools to produce over 2000 visualizations of student and teacher level survey data to populate a client's summary reports
- Wrote R scripts to review data sets in longitudinal surveys to meet compliance standards
- Developed over 5 unique animations for social media distribution

# FREELANCE/INDEPENDENT CONTRACTOR

The Ballengee Group (November 2014 - February 2015)

- Created a database of baseball performance and salary data exclusively using R software
- Modeled salary expectations for over 80 major and minor league baseball players across a 10 year period using machine learning methods

www.mikelee.co (November 2014 - Present)

 Online portfolio of data visualizations and independent analyses; implemented with Bootstrap and hosted on GitHub

# SPECIAL EDUCATION TEACHER

Milwaukee Public Schools (Aug 2011 - June 2013)

- Utilized performance data to develop lesson plans, activities, and interventions appropriate for students with diverse learning needs and disabilities
- Collaborated with staff to create IEPs for students with significant behavioral challenges
- Moderated behavior charts and implemented effective classroom management techniques

# **EDUCATION**

# MASTERS OF ARTS. **URBAN EDUCATION**

2013

Cardinal Stritch University, Milwaukee, WI

# BACHELOR OF SCIENCE. **PSYCHOLOGY**

University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI

# **SPECIALTIES**

Data Analysis & Processing Data Visualization Web Development Web Scraping R Package Development **Technical Writing** Workshop Moderation

#### SKILLS

#### **Data Toolbox**

R // Python // SQL // Shiny // Excel

#### Web Development

HTML5 // D3.is // CSS // Bootstrap // Git

# Intangibles

Lesson Planning // Differentiated Instruction